Guide to the James Thomas Flexner Papers 1920s - 1990s MS 220
New-York Historical Society
James Thomas Flexner papers
1920s - 1990s
New-York Historical Society
Flexner, James Thomas, 1908-2003
MS 220
58 Linear feet (in 58 record cartons).
Drafts, galleys, scrapbooks, typescripts, index cards, research notes, subject files, and correspondence of James Thomas Flexner (1908-2003), the prolific author of twenty-six works on American art, history, and biography. Flexner was perhaps best known for his three-volume History of American Painting (1947-1962), and his four-volume George Washington: A Biography (1965-1972), the final installment of which won the 1973 National Book Award for Biography.
Arrangement
The James Thomas Flexner Papers are sorted in twenty series. Series I through XVIII contain the research notes pertaining to one or more of Flexner's published books. Series XIX and XX contain drafts of unpublished novels, miscellaneous correspondence, and subject files. Since much of the material within each series is undated, the collection is sorted chronologically by publication date. File titles are derived from those in a 2003 inventory of the collection; these were transcribed, apparently, from Flexner's original container labels.
Series I
Doctors on Horseback: Pioneers of American Medicine, published 1937
Series II
America's Old Masters: First Artists of the New World, published 1939
Series III
William Henry Welch and the Heroic Age of American Medicine, published 1941
Series IV
Steamboats Come True: American Inventors in Action, published 1944
Series V
History of American Painting, 3 volumes, published 1947-1962
Series VI
A Short History of American Painting, published 1950, reissued 1957
Series VII
The Traitor and the Spy: Benedict Arnold and John André, published 1953
Series VIII
Gilbert Stuart: A Great Life in Brief, published 1955
Series IX
Mohawk Baronet: Sir William Johnson of New York, published 1959
Series X
George Washington: A Biography, 4 volumes plus abridgment, published 1965-1972, 1974
Series XI
The World of Winslow Homer 1836–1910, published 1966
Series XII
Nineteenth Century American Painting, published 1970
Series XIII
The Face of Liberty: Founders of the United States, published 1975
Series XIV
The Young Hamilton: A Biography, published 1978
Series XV
States Dyckman: American Loyalist, published 1980
Series XVI
An American Saga: The Story of Helen Thomas and Simon Flexner, published 1984
Series XVII
Poems of the Twenties, published 1991
Series XVIII
Maverick's Progress: An Autobiography, published 1996
Series XIX
Unpublished novels, undated
Series XX
Miscellaneous correspondence and subject files, circa 1933-1971
Biographical Note
James Thomas Flexner was born in Manhattan on January 13, 1908 to Simon and Helen (Thomas) Flexner. Simon Flexner (1863–1946), a physician, scientist, and professor of experimental pathology at the University of Pennsylvania, served as first director of the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research. Helen (Thomas) Flexner (1871–1956), a professor of English at Bryn Mawr College (where her sister served as president), was connected by family marriages to the philosopher Bertrand Russell and the art critic Bernard Berenson.
As a child James Thomas Flexner found reading and writing difficult. He overcame his dyslexia one day as he sat in Central Park staring at a page of Beatrix Potter's The Tale of Peter Rabbit, when the printed marks suddenly formed themselves into words. This achievement so inspired Flexner that from then on writing his own stories became the focus of his life. Educated at the progressive Lincoln School of Columbia University's Teachers College, he went on to graduate magna cum laude with a degree in English from Harvard University in 1929. Soon after he was hired to write human interest pieces for the New York Herald Tribune, but left by 1931 for a position with the New York City Department of Health. He resigned the following year to devote his full time to writing.
His first book, Doctors on Horseback: Pioneers of American Medicine (1937), was inspired by the work of his father. (Simon Flexner is probably best known for developing a serum treatment for spinal meningitis.) From medicine he gravitated to art history, with America's Old Masters: First Artists of the New World (1939), a study of the painters Benjamin West, John Singleton Copley, Charles Willson Peale, and Gilbert Stuart. This work, and Flexner's three-volume History of American Painting (1947–1962), helped establish the subject as an academic specialty, despite the author's lack of formal training in the field.
American history and biography, too, supplied compelling material for Flexner's talents. 1953 saw publication of The Traitor and the Spy: Benedict Arnold and John André. This was followed in 1959 by Mohawk Baronet: Sir William Johnson of New York. But George Washington would prove Flexner's most enduring and rewarding subject.
The four-volume George Washington: A Biography, appeared between 1965 and 1972. Critics hailed Flexner's portrait for demystifying Washington, for moving beyond "the marble image" and bringing the hero "down from Olympus." The final volume, Anguish and Farewell, 1793–1799, won the 1973 National Book Award for Biography and a special Pulitzer citation. In 1974 Flexner published a single volume abridgment of the series, Washington: The Indispensable Man. Flexner's Washington works were adapted as television miniseries in the mid-1980s starring Barry Bostwick as the first president.
Flexner's later biographies, The Young Hamilton (1978) and States Dyckman: American Loyalist (1980) were followed by volumes of a personal nature: An American Saga: The Story of Helen Thomas and Simon Flexner (1984) and Maverick's Progress (1996), an autobiography.
James Flexner married professional singer Beatrice Hudson (1919–1998) in 1950. The couple had one daughter, Helen. Flexner died, age 95, in Manhattan, on February 13, 2003.
______________________________
This note is based on Flexner's obituary in the New York Times, February 16, 2003 ("James Thomas Flexner, Washington Biographer, 95 Dies"), his entry in the Dictionary of Art Historians, and information from his autobiography, Maverick's Progress (1996).
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
James Thomas Flexner gave the bulk of the collection to the New-York Historical Society on October 11, 1974. (In the acknowledgements to his 1996 autobiography, Maverick's Progress, Flexner thanks the Society for its more than sixty years of hospitality. During that time he was accorded research and writing space in the library.) Donations of material continued through the 1990s and possibly as late as 2003, the year of Flexner's death.
Related Materials
In addition to copies of most of Flexner's published books, the New-York Historical Society also holds typescripts for his "The Traitor and the Spy: Benedict Arnold and John André " (1953) and "Mohawk Baronet: Sir William Johnson of New York" (1959).
Scope and Contents
The James Thomas Flexner Papers include the raw materials—drafts, galleys, scrapbooks, typescripts, index cards, research notes, subject files, and correspondence—that the author used to create most of his twenty-six books on art history and American history and biography. Not every format exists for each book project. Because the collection has not been processed below the box level (it was inventoried in 2003 and rehoused but not reordered in 2019), it is difficult to know the extent of topic coverage or the date range of items. The container list below attempts to minimize the haphazard placement of related material by grouping it under its common project title. Interested researchers should consult each box listed under a particular series, except for Series XX, which contains miscellaneous correspondence and subject files that are scattered throughout most of the collection's 58 boxes.
American loyalists; Art historians -- United States.; Biographers -- United States.; Historians -- United States.; Inventors -- United States.; Medicine -- United States; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American; Physicians -- United States; Poems -- United States -- 20th century; Steamboats -- United States.; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783.; United States -- History -- Confederation -- 1783-1789; United States -- History -- Constitutional period -- 1789-1809; United States -- Politics and government -- 1775-1783; United States -- Politics and government -- 1783-1809; Drafts (documents); Galley proofs.; Index cards; Letters (correspondence); Notebooks.; Research (documents); Scrapbooks.; Typescripts.; André, John, 1751-1780; Arnold, Benedict, 1741-1801; Beaumont, William, 1785-1853; Copley, John Singleton, 1738-1815; Drake, Daniel, 1785-1852; Dyckman, States Morris; Flexner, Helen Thomas, 1871-1956; Flexner, James Thomas, 1908-2003; Flexner, Simon, 1863-1946; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804; Homer, Winslow, 1836-1910; Johnson, William, 1715-1774; McDowell, Ephraim, 1771-1830; Morgan, John, 1735-1789; Peale, Charles Willson, 1741-1827; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; Stuart, Gilbert, 1755-1828; Washington, George, 1732-1799; Welch, William Henry, 1850-1934; West, Benjamin, 1738-1820
- Series I. Doctors on Horseback: Pioneers of American Medicine, published 1937
  - Doctors on Horseback – Daniel Drake, Ephraim McDowell, The Death of Pain [card file], before 1937 (Offsite-box 8)
  - Doctors on Horseback – John Morgan, Benjamin Rush [card file], before 1937 (Offsite-box 26)
  - Doctors on Horseback – William Beaumont, Credits, Illustrations, Bibliographies [card file], before 1937 (Offsite-box 33)
  - Doctors on Horseback [manuscript], before 1937 (Offsite-box 54)
- Series II. America's Old Masters: First Artists of the New World, published 1939
  - America's Old Masters – West [card file], before 1939 (Offsite-box 1)
  - America's Old Masters – Copley Notes [bundle], before 1939 (Offsite-box 51)
  - America's Old Masters – scrapbook of reviews, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 53)
  - America's Old Masters [manuscript], before 1939 (Offsite-box 54)
- Series III. William Henry Welch and the Heroic Age of American Medicine, published 1941
  - Later / Clintonville Welch [folder], before 1941 (Offsite-box 39)
- Series IV. Steamboats Come True: American Inventors in Action, published 1944
  - Steamboats – After Publication – Correspondence [folder], before 1944 (Offsite-box 18)
  - Steamboats (1 of 2), before 1944 (Offsite-box 49)
  - Steamboats (2 of 2), before 1944 (Offsite-box 50)
  - Steamboats [page proofs], before 1944 (Offsite-box 54)
- Series V. History of American Painting, 3 volumes, published 1947-1962
  - Volume 1: First Flowers of Our Wilderness: American Painting, the Colonial Period, published 1947
    - First Flowers – Land Scene List [card file], before 1947 (Offsite-box 1)
    - First Flowers of our Wilderness Before 1730 – Smibert – Feke – 18th Cent. Artists Alphabetical [card file], before 1947 (Offsite-box 26)
    - Glass plate negatives – First Flowers of the Wilderness (offset section – 11/7/67), before 1947 (Offsite-box 31)
    - First Flowers [manuscript], before 1947 (Offsite-box 54)
    - First Flowers [page proofs], before 1947 (Offsite-box 54)
  - Volume 2: The Light of Distant Skies (1760-1835), published 1954
    - Light of Distant Skies Artists [card file], before 1954 (Offsite-box 16)
    - Light of Distant Skies – 2nd Half [card file], before 1954 (Offsite-box 22)
    - Light of Distant Skies [manuscript], before 1954 (Offsite-box 54)
  - Volume 3: That Wilder Image: The Native School, published 1962
    - 19__ – Volume III of the History of Painting [card file], before 1962 (Offsite-box 8)
    - Wilder Artists, A-Z [card file], before 1962 (Offsite-box 15)
    - Wilder Image – Artists A to D [card file], before 1962 (Offsite-box 19)
    - Wilder – Categories [card file], before 1962 (Offsite-box 21)
    - Dover Publications reprint (1970) of That Wilder Image (Offsite-box 53)
    - That Wilder Image II (1 of 2), before 1962 (Offsite-box 55)
    - That Wilder Image II (2 of 2), before 1962 (Offsite-box 56)
- Series VI. A Short History of American Painting, published 1950, reissued 1957
  - Pocket Book – Post Vision [card file], before 1950 or circa 1957 (Offsite-box 1)
- Series VII. The Traitor and the Spy: Benedict Arnold and John André, published 1953
  - Arnold – Notes & Play (1 of 2), before 1953 (Offsite-box 4)
  - Arnold – Notes & Play (2 of 2), before 1953 (Offsite-box 5)
  - Traitor Reviews – Duplicates (1 of 2), before 1953 (Offsite-box 18)
  - Traitor Reviews – Duplicates (2 of 2), before 1953 (Offsite-box 19)
  - Benedict Arnold – Television Script, before 1953 (Offsite-box 37)
  - Arnold Play [folder], before 1953 (Offsite-box 52)
  - Final Draft, Traitor & Spy, before 1953 (Offsite-box 54)
- Series VIII. Gilbert Stuart: A Great Life in Brief, published 1955
  - Stuart [draft], before 1955 (Offsite-box 12)
  - Stuart Harding / Columbia Bits [card file], before 1955 (Offsite-box 12)
- Series IX. Mohawk Baronet: Sir William Johnson of New York, published 1959
  - Johnson, 1767 – Categories [card file], before 1959 (Offsite-box 9)
  - Johnson – Appendix – Illus. – Names Not sorted [card file], before 1959 (Offsite-box 11)
  - Johnson – Birth – 1764 [card file], before 1959 (Offsite-box 23)
  - Sir William Johnson – Chaps I-IX – First Draft, before 1959 (Offsite-box 27)
  - Sir William Johnson – Mohawk Baronet, before 1959 (Offsite-box 27)
  - William Johnson Chronology [folder], before 1959 (Offsite-box 27)
  - Mohawk Baronet Page Proof [envelope], before 1959 (Offsite-box 27)
  - Mohawk Baronet – Final Draft [envelope], before 1959 (Offsite-box 37)
- Series X. George Washington: A Biography, 4 volumes plus abridgment, published 1965-1972, 1974
  - Volume 1: The Forge of Experience, 1732-1775, published 1965
    - Forge of Experience – Rough Sheets / Gallies [sic], before 1965 (Offsite-box 13)
    - Washington – Volume One [card file], before 1965 (Offsite-box 32)
  - Volume 2: George Washington in the American Revolution, 1775-1783, published 1968
    - Washington II [card file], before 1968 (Offsite-box 10)
    - Washington – Revolution I [card file], before 1968 (Offsite-box 20)
    - Working Carbon of George Washington in the American Revolution, before 1968 (Offsite-box 25)
    - Washington – Revolution II [card file], before 1968 (Offsite-box 35)
    - Washington II – Second Draft [envelope], before 1968 (Offsite-box 36)
    - Manuscript – George Washington in the American Revolution (sealed box containing mss from Little Brown and Company to JTF, postmarked 5/27/66), before 1968 (Offsite-box 38)
    - Manuscript – Washington in the Revolution, before 1968 (Offsite-box 39)
  - Volume 3: George Washington and the New Nation, 1783-1793, published 1970
    - Washington III – General [card file], before 1970 (Offsite-box 24)
    - Sheets: Washington in the American Revolution. A few carbons, Vol. III (1 of 2), before 1970 (Offsite-box 34)
    - Sheets: Washington in the American Revolution. A few carbons, Vol. III (2 of 2), before 1970 (Offsite-box 35)
    - Washington III carbon with corrections [microfilm reel], before 1970 (Offsite-box 38)
    - Sealed box containing mss [George Washington III] from Little Brown and Company to JTF, postmarked 1/8/71, before 1972 (Offsite-box 38)
  - Volume 4: Anguish and Farewell, 1793-1799, published 1972
    - Sealed box containing mss [George Washington IV] from Little Brown and Company to JTF, postmarked 4/11/73, before 1972 (Offsite-box 7)
    - Washington IV – Final Draft to Typist, before 1972 (Offsite-box 15)
    - Washington IV [2 microfilm reels], before 1972 (Offsite-box 38)
  - Abridgment: Washington: The Indispensable Man, published 1974
    - Sealed box containing mss from Little Brown and Company to JTF, postmarked 2/22/82 [holds manuscript of Washington: The Indispensable Man], before 1974 (Offsite-box 31)
  - [George Washington materials, uncertain placement]
    - Early Drafts – Washington (1 of 2), undated (Offsite-box 2)
    - Early Drafts – Washington (2 of 2), undated (Offsite-box 3)
    - [Washington] [card file], undated (Offsite-box 17)
    - Washington 1984 [hanging file] (Offsite-box 27)
    - From: Early Drafts Washington [folder], undated (Offsite-box 32)
    - [George Washington] [galley], undated (Offsite-box 39)
    - [George Washington], undated (Offsite-box 39)
    - Flexner – Washington, undated (Offsite-box 44)
    - Douglas Southall Freeman, George Washington: A Biography, vol. 6, "Patriot and President", 1975 (Offsite-box 53)
- Series XI. The World of Winslow Homer 1836–1910, published 1966
  - Time Correspondence / World of Winslow Homer [folder], 1964-1965 (Offsite-box 18)
  - Sheets for Winslow Homer – Washington for [rest of label missing], before 1966 (Offsite-box 57)
- Series XII. Nineteenth Century American Painting, published 1970
  - 19th Century Painting – Corrections Carbon, before 1970 (Offsite-box 11)
  - 19th Century American Painting – Original Ms. with Flexner and M.R. [Milton Rugoff] corrections – this does not go to printer, before 1970 (Offsite-box 17)
  - Flexner – Painting – Central – Gathered for 19th Cent. Book [card file], before 1970 (Offsite-box 33)
- Series XIII. The Face of Liberty: Founders of the United States, published 1975
  - Two copies of published volume., 1975 (Offsite-box 53)
- Series XIV. The Young Hamilton: A Biography, published 1978
  - Hamilton, before 1978 (Offsite-box 14)
  - Flexner – Hamilton Original Draft, before 1978 (Offsite-box 24)
  - Hamilton – Copying Draft [envelope], before 1978 (Offsite-box 36)
- Series XV. States Dyckman: American Loyalist, published 1980
  - Dyckman, before 1980 (Offsite-box 43)
  - [States Dyckman], before 1980 (Offsite-box 48)
  - Boscobel c. 1977 – English tvp. 1978 – Mount Vernon & Son & Lumiere, circa 1977 (Offsite-box 51)
- Series XVI. An American Saga: The Story of Helen Thomas and Simon Flexner, published 1984
  - Helen Thomas Flexner (mother)
    - Helen to Bertie – Annotated copies of letters from Helen N. Thomas to Bertrand Russell [hanging file], circa 1903-1929 (Offsite-box 10)
    - Done to be filed – Notes re "Bertie-Helen," copies of letters from Helen to Bertie, copies from Bertrand Russell's America and review of same from "Studies in History of Society," Vol. II, Nos. 1 and 2, Fall and Spring, 1970 [folder] (Offsite-box 10)
    - Copies of letters from Alys R. to Helen Thomas [folder], circa 1899-1928 (Offsite-box 10)
    - Mildred Whitall – Correspondence, photographs [file], before 1984 (Offsite-box 19)
    - Helen to Bertie B Series – Copies of letters from Helen to Bertie [envelope], before 1984 (Offsite-box 32)
    - Helen – 19003 [sic] – Non Courting – Notes, annotated copies of correspondence, drafts, correspondence [envelope], circa 1903? (Offsite-box 36)
    - M. Carey Thomas – Diary – Copy [envelope], before 1984 (Offsite-box 36)
    - Thomas S. Whitall – Backgrounds Pearsall Smiths – Research notes [envelope], before 1984 (Offsite-box 36)
    - Helen – 1897 – Misc. re that date – Grace's Troubles – Notes, copies of correspondence [envelope], circa 1897? (Offsite-box 37)
    - Helen Whitall Flexner – Mother's Papers – Letters to William / Philosophical Society – Correspondence, before 1984 (Offsite-box 38)
    - Thomas, 1860-1880's – Death of Mary Whitall – James Carey Thomas – Research notes, drafts, copies [envelope], circa 1860-1880s (Offsite-box 42)
    - Helen 1889-1896 – Research notes, drafts, copies [envelope] (Offsite-box 42)
  - Simon Flexner (father)
    - "1925" – Notes on S.F. Diaries, correspondence, passport Loose drafts & correspondence [hanging file], circa 1925? (Offsite-box 19)
    - Simon Flexner Diary, 1921-1925 [photocopy] (Offsite-box 22)
    - Simon – Copy Flow of Diaries [photocopy], before 1984 (Offsite-box 23)
    - James Thomas Flexner's Note on Autobiographical Conversations with Simon Flexner [folder], circa 1936-1939 (Offsite-box 32)
    - Simon Flexner – University of Penna. – Scientific Work – Drafts, notes, research [envelope], before 1984 (Offsite-box 36)
    - Simon Hopkins – Research re SF at Johns Hopkins, notes, etc. [envelope], before 1984 (Offsite-box 37)
    - Abe & Anne – Flexner Siblings – Research notes, drafts, copies [envelope], before 1984 (Offsite-box 37)
    - Simon – Louisville – Flexner Background – Research notes, correspondence, drafts, copies [envelope], before 1984 (Offsite-box 42)
    - Flexner Simon – Life 1900-1903 – Rockefeller Institute – Research notes, drafts, copies [envelope] (Offsite-box 42)
    - SF Flexner Diaries I, 1917-1920 [photocopy, 4 folders] (Offsite-box 53)
  - General
    - Notes – American Saga, before 1984 (Offsite-box 9)
    - American Saga Ms., before 1984 (Offsite-box 29)
    - American Saga – Final Carbon – 1-25 [envelope], before 1984 (Offsite-box 36)
    - American Saga – Final Copy – 26-50 – Carbon [envelope], before 1984 (Offsite-box 37)
    - American Saga – Source References – Carbon [envelope], before 1984 (Offsite-box 37)
    - American Saga [final draft?], before 1984 (Offsite-box 45)
- Series XVII. Poems of the Twenties, published 1991
  - Poetry Notebook I, undated (Offsite-box 53)
  - James Thomas Flexner Verse, 1924-1931 (Offsite-box 53)
- Series XVIII. Maverick's Progress: An Autobiography, published 1996
  - "A Rage to Write: The Making of a Biographer – Box Two" – Typescript, before 1996 (Offsite-box 20)
  - Freshman at Harvard – Copies of letters from JTF to his parents, n.d. [folder], [1925] (Offsite-box 21)
  - Sophomore / Harvard 1926 – Annotated copies of letters from JTF to his parents, n.d. [folder] (Offsite-box 21)
  - Junior-Senior / Harvard – Annotated copies of letters from JTF to his parents, n.d. [folder], [1927-1928] (Offsite-box 21)
- Series XIX. Unpublished novels, undated
  - "Dogs Shall Eat Jezebel" – Xerox [envelope], undated (Offsite-box 32)
  - "Enter and Possess" [typescript], undated (Offsite-box 16)
- Series XX. Miscellaneous correspondence and subject files, circa 1933-1971
  - A-R – Assorted files of correspondence and admin. material (1 of 2), 1951-1962 (Offsite-box 46)
  - A-R – Assorted files of correspondence and admin. material (2 of 2), 1951-1962 (Offsite-box 47)
  - A, 1963-1971 (Offsite-box 52)
  - Adams I – Adams Notes for Historical Society [card file], undated (Offsite-box 7)
  - Ag's letters – Correspondence [folder], undated (Offsite-box 18)
  - American Heritage, 1962-1971 (Offsite-box 52)
  - Article Ideas [card file], undated (Offsite-box 1)
  - [Autobiographical notes] [binder], undated (Offsite-box 53)
  - B, 1963-1971 (Offsite-box 52)
  - Bushnell—Material, undated (Offsite-box 52)
  - C – culled 1952 – Correspondence [folder], 1945-1950 (Offsite-box 18)
  - C, 1963-1971 (Offsite-box 52)
  - Century Association, through 1971 (Offsite-box 52)
  - City Noise, vol. II [page proofs], undated (Offsite-box 54)
  - Columbia Caper – Notes [folder], undated (Offsite-box 27)
  - [Correspondence] Assorted files of correspondence and drafts (Reviewed by JTF October – November 1992), 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 28)
  - [Correspondence] Assorted files of correspondence and drafts, 1950s-1970s (Offsite-box 58)
  - D, 1963-1971 (Offsite-box 52)
  - Dictionary of American Biography, supplement three, 1941-1945, 1973 (Offsite-box 53)
  - Digressionists, undated (Offsite-box 52)
  - E, 1959-1971 (Offsite-box 52)
  - English Articles – Correspondence, mss [folder], 1945 (Offsite-box 18)
  - F, 1959-1971 (Offsite-box 52)
  - Faquanzi's Muses [card file], undated (Offsite-box 1)
  - Farrar Straus, undated (Offsite-box 52)
  - [Financial] Personal financial records, including tax returns and correspondence, 1952-1967 (Offsite-box 6)
  - Financial, 1953-1957, 1962-1963 (Offsite-box 40)
  - For Writing Anthology [folder], before 1998? (Offsite-box 53)